{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The event for which this man is most remembered for occurred on March 2, 1962. During that game, the Knicks deliberately fouled other players to keep the ball away from this man, who at the time played for the Philadelphia Warriors. For 10 points, name this man who holds the NBA record for most points in a regular season with 4,029, and who was the first and only NBA player to score 100 points in a game.",
      "answer": "Wilt Chamberlain"
    },
    {
      "question": "With Douglas Fairbanks, Mary Pickford, and Charlie Chaplin, this man co-founded United Artists. A film by this director was the first film to be shown privately at the White House and was praised by Woodrow Wilson. That film by this director was criticized for its positive portrayal of the Ku Klux Klan. For 10 points, name this director of Birth of a Nation.",
      "answer": "D.W. Griffith"
    },
    {
      "question": "After a 1515 French victory outside this city, the Swiss Confederacy swore an eternal truce with the French. This site of the Battle of Marignano was ruled by Ludovico il Moro, who commissioned Leonardo’s The Last Supper. Until falling under French and Spanish control, this city was ruled by the Sforza family. For 10 points, name this Northern Italian city.",
      "answer": "Milan"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man shocked both Catholic and Protestant countries when he ordered the burning of Michael Servetus. This man, who explained his religious views in the book Institutes of the Christian Religion¸ advocated the \"TULIP\" philosophy as the civil authority in Geneva. For 10 points, name this founder of a strict, predestination-focused Protestant theology.",
      "answer": "John Calvin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This complex was home to a nail factory whose profitability changed its owner's views on slavery for the worse. This complex was in disrepair when Uriah Levy purchased it in 1836. The central building at this plantation was designed in the Palladian style and overlooks Charlottesville. For 10 points, name this home estate of Thomas Jefferson.",
      "answer": "Monticello"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man rose to the head of his party after he was targeted by the Zhongshan Warship Incident. This man and his wife propounded the semi-fascist New Life Movement, and he was the first commandant of the Whampoa Military Academy. His wife Soong May-ling supposedly had an affair with Wendell Wilkie, and he succeeded Sun Yat-Sen as leader of the KMT. For 10, points, name this longtime president of Taiwan and nationalist leader during the Chinese Civil War.",
      "answer": "Chiang Kai-Shek"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man coined the term \"timocracy\" for a government by property-owners, which he deemed the second-best of five possible governments. He used the parable of the divided line to explain the process of understanding and analogized the visible world as shadows on the wall of a cave. For 10 points, name this Greek who advocated \"philosopher-kings\" in The Republic.",
      "answer": "Plato"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's memoir noted that the FBI sent agents to take notes on his bar mitzvah in an attempt to prove his parents' Communist Party membership, which he admitted. This man wrote His Holiness, a biography of Pope John Paul II, and the Hillary Clinton bio A Woman in Charge. For 10 points, name this reporter who broke the Watergate story with Bob Woodward.",
      "answer": "Carl Bernstein"
    },
    {
      "question": "This text is the subject of the Supreme Court case Minersville v. Gobitis. This text was originally recited while saluting outward, a recommendation changed after World War II. Michael Newdow filed several lawsuits attempting to remove a phrase added in the 1950s, \"under God,\" from this text. For 10 points, name this Francis Bellamy-written ode to the U.S. flag.",
      "answer": "Pledge of Allegiance"
    },
    {
      "question": "This type of song was repopularized by the Fisk Jubilee Singers. A song of this type written by Charles Wesley says \"My brother, you ought to been there;\" another of these songs repeats \"Tell old Pharaoh, let my people go.\" For 10 points, \"Roll, Jordan, Roll\" and \"Go Down Moses\" are examples of what kind of Christian song often sung by slaves in the antebellum South?",
      "answer": "spirituals NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author lived among the East End poor for six months to write The People of the Abyss, advocated for the genocide of China in \"The Unparalleled Invasion,\" and described a dystopian U.S. in The Iron Heel. For 10 points, name this American author who chronicled Yukon gold rushers in \"To Build a Fire\" and a novel about the dog Buck, The Call of the Wild.",
        "answer": "Jack London"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What author extended London's The People of the Abyss by writing Down and Out in Paris and London before creating his own dystopia in which Winston Smith visits Room 101?",
        "answer": "George Orwell"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman was travelling with Laura Havilland when she was bruised by a streetcar conductor, leading to the desegration of public transit in Washington, D.C. Earlier, this woman said she wanted to \"fill her pint of intellect\" in a speech in Akron. For 10 points, name this former slave who advocated for abolition and women's equality in the \"Ain't I A Woman\" speech.",
        "answer": "Sojourner Truth"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What attorney, who later became President of the United States upon the assassination of James Garfield, filed the suit that desegregated public transit in New York City?",
        "answer": "Chester Alan Arthur"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Bernard de Launay was killed during this event. It was lead by Pierre-Augustin Hulin, and partially sparked by the dismissal of the finance minister Jacques Necker three days before. Celebrated on a holiday observed on July 14, this event liberated a mere seven prisoners. For 10 points, name this 1789 event in which an angry mob sacked a Parisian prison.",
        "answer": "storming of the Bastille"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What earlier resident of the Bastille wrote Candide (can-DEED)?",
        "answer": "Voltaire"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "French citizens accused of this activity were often charged with “state of indignity.” Jozef Tiso was convicted and hanged for this crime in Czechoslovakia. The Épuration was a series of trials in France for this crime, of which Philippe Pétain and other leaders in the Vichy government were found guilty. For 10 points, name this crime of assisting an occupying army.",
        "answer": "Nazi collaboration"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What country's collaborationist regime was led by Vidkun Quisling and was the site of a heavy water plant intended for Germany's nuclear program?",
        "answer": "Norway"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Christopher replaced George Morgan on this show as chaplain Mulcahy. This show had two spinoffs, including the contemporary-set Trapper John, M.D. This TV show was based on a 1970 Robert Altman film, and its 1983 finale remains the highest-rated episode of a scripted TV show ever. For 10 points, name this sitcom set during the Korean War.",
        "answer": "M*A*S*H"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The second-most watched non-sports broadcast in American history was what late 1970s miniseries, based on an Alex Haley novel about his slave ancestors?",
        "answer": "Roots"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A park in an old capital of this nation kept a herd of inviolable sacred deer. Cord-marked pottery was a hallmark of its Stone Age Jomon culture. This modern-day country made tombs called kofun during an era when it began importing Chinese culture and received Buddhist envoys from Korea. For 10 points, name this Asian nation whose Yamato clan ruled it from Nara prefecture.",
        "answer": "Japan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Jomon people made midden mounds out of what natural objects, whose cowrie variety were gathered from water for use as currency in pre-colonial America?",
        "answer": "seashells"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Subgroups called iwi divided these people, who argued based on language differences that they never meant to cede sovereignty to William Hobson in the 1840 Treaty of Waitangi. Hone Heke was a chief of these people. Some of their men mark themselves with swirling lines of ta moko, a type of carved-in ink tattoo. For 10 points, name these indigenous inhabitants of New Zealand.",
        "answer": "Maōri people"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Western weapon, a descendant of the arquebus, was first traded to the Ngapuhi iwi in 1807, kicking off a set of namesake \"wars\" on North Island?",
        "answer": "muskets"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The \"flag-follower\" expeditions of miners departed from this city in the eighteenth century. The painting Independence or Death depicts events that took place in this city, which are also remembered at the Ipiranga (ee-pee-RON-guh) Monument. For 10 points, name this city where Pedro I declared the independence of Brazil, which is now the country's most populous.",
        "answer": "São Paulo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which other Brazilian city has been the largest city entirely within the Amazon rain forest for decades, and hosted 2014 FIFA World Cup matches?",
        "answer": "Manaus NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "EUROPEAN CITIES IN THE 1940’s",
      "prompt": "Which European city...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the site of an airlift into the city's Soviet zone in 1948?",
          "answer": "Berlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was where military tribunals were held to try Nazi leaders?",
          "answer": "Nuremberg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a conference where the United States, Great Britain, and the Soviet Union agreed to divide Germany into four occupation zones?",
          "answer": "Potsdam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the largest battle in history and repulsed the German army from its invasion of the Soviet Union?",
          "answer": "Stalingrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of the largest Jewish ghetto uprising against the Nazis in 1943?",
          "answer": "Warsaw"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a massive evacuation of Allied troops to Great Britain?",
          "answer": "Dunkirk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the city where Ernest Hemingway claimed to liberate the bar at the Ritz hotel in 1944?",
          "answer": "Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the city where the Nazis failed to destroy the Ponte Vecchio (PON-tay VEK-ee-yo) over the Arno River?",
          "answer": "Florence"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE FRENCH REVOLUTION",
      "prompt": "During the French Revolution, what",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "King of France was guillotined?",
          "answer": "Louis XVI"
        },
        {
          "question": "Queen of France apocryphally said “let them eat cake.”?",
          "answer": "Marie Antoinette"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Committee of Public Safety was turned on during the Thermidorian Reaction?",
          "answer": "Maximilien de Robespierre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary was killed in his bath by Charlotte Corday?",
          "answer": "Jean-Paul Marat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Oath was sworn by the National Assembly after it was locked out of its planned meeting space?",
          "answer": "Tennis Court Oath"
        },
        {
          "question": "Three values were enshrined in the national motto of Revolutionary France?",
          "answer": "Liberté, égalité, fraternité"
        },
        {
          "question": "Seventeen article charter of human rights was adopted by the National Assembly in 1789?",
          "answer": "Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Province had a namesake Royalist counterrevolution from 1793-1796?",
          "answer": "the Vendee"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "SUPREME COURT JUSTICES",
      "prompt": "What Supreme Court Justice…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Oversaw the desegregation of schools in Brown v. Board?",
          "answer": "Earl Warren"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the current Chief Justice?",
          "answer": "John Roberts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first black Justice, appointed in 1967?",
          "answer": "Thurgood Marshall"
        },
        {
          "question": "Established the principle of judicial review in Marbury v. Madison?",
          "answer": "John Marshall"
        },
        {
          "question": "Survived the Anita Hill hearings in 1991?",
          "answer": "Clarence Thomas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Delivered the Dred Scott decision?",
          "answer": "Roger Taney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the current \"swing vote\" in many rulings?",
          "answer": "Anthony Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote the Roe v. Wade decision after research at the Mayo Clinic?",
          "answer": "Harry Blackmun NHBB B 2014-2015"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's treatise Mechanics advanced the notion that inertia is derived from the mass of every other body in the universe, now known as his \"principle.\" His History of Mechanics introduced to Einstein the idea of non-absolute space. This German (20 pts)",
        "philosopher of science who also discovered shock waves produced when the (10 pts)",
        "speed of sound is exceeded. For 10 points, identify this man who thus lends his name to a \"number\" denoting the proportion to the speed of sound."
      ],
      "answer": "Ernst Mach"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this war, the Titulus Regius was repealed. During this war, a king negotiated the Treaty of Piquniny with “the Universal Spider,” Louis XI. A leader of one of this war’s sides married Elizabeth (20 pts)",
        "Woodville, thus alienating his ally Warwick the Kingmaker. This war ended after (10 pts)",
        "Richard III was defeated at the Battle of Bosworth Field. For 10 points, name this conflict between the houses of Lancaster and York, which were represented by red and white flowers."
      ],
      "answer": "War of the Roses"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In response to this event, a system was announced in which alternate-day accessibility was determined by the last digit of a car's license plate. This event, a classic example of an economic (20 pts)",
        "\"supply shock,\" was a response to perceived U.S. support of Israel in the Yom Kippur War. This event was engineered by (10 pts)",
        "OPEC and devastated the economy under Richard Nixon. For 10 points, identify this 1973 event which caused long lines at gas stations."
      ],
      "answer": "OPEC oil embargo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Judica-Cordiglia recordings purportedly captured transmissions from the \"lost\" group of these people, whose existence or death is believed to have been suppressed. One of these people died in a 1968 (20 pts)",
        "fighter jet crash, seven years after using the Vostok. These people included (10 pts)",
        "Valentina Tereshkova and Yuri Gagarin. For 10 points, identify these people who included the first-ever man in space, and were the stars of the Soviet space program."
      ],
      "answer": "cosmonauts"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In retirement from politics, this man wrote a bizarre novel about a conspiracy to destroy the United States, entitled The Canfield Decision. This man was mocked as receiving \"the greatest deal since the Lord spared Isaac on the mountaintop\" when he was able to plead to only (20 pts)",
        "tax evasion after accepting substantial bribes, causing his 1973 (10 pts)",
        "resignation. For 10 points, name this Greek-American, and Maryland-born Vice-President under Richard Nixon."
      ],
      "answer": "Spiro Agnew"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Police in this city fought with demonstrators at Admiralty, Causeway Bay, and Mong Kok during protests that were centered at the Connaught and Harcourt Road area. Those protests in this city, grew out of the (20 pts)",
        "Occupy Central movement founded by Joshua Wong and Lester Shum. (10 pts)",
        "For 10 points, name this city where the \"Umbrella Revolution\" movement seeks to accelerate democratization following a 2014 decision on electoral reforms from China, which has governed this city since 1997."
      ],
      "answer": "Hong Kong"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's security forces were denounced as \"doberman thugs\" by the U.S. President after attacking Billy Ford. This home of the Dignity Battalions was where the Vatican embassy was targeted by loud (20 pts)",
        "rock music in Operation Nifty Package. The U.S. signed the Carter-Torrjos Treaty with this country, which was invaded in Operation (10 pts)",
        "Just Cause. For 10 points, name this country where Manuel Noriega was displaced from overseeing a canal."
      ],
      "answer": "Panama"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 1920s, this party divided into \"black and tan\" and \"lily white\" factions in a dispute over allowing African-American support. A dissident faction of this party briefly broke away in 1870 under Carl Schurz and cross-nominated (20 pts)",
        "Horace Greeley for President in 1872; that party appended the word (10 pts)",
        "\"liberal\" to this party's name. For 10 points, name this party that engineered Reconstruction, and won the Presidency under Abraham Lincoln."
      ],
      "answer": "Republican Party NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ]
}